[SPEAKER_00]: Establishing yourself in the wholesome state, in that way, staying there, and learning to decompose in there, in wholesomeness, wherever that wholesomeness might be.
How?
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me ask you that, Swami.
[SPEAKER_00]: How are you composing?
[SPEAKER_01]: How would that composure come to be then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, as you're saying,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's being able to see the determination, or the... Yeah, the relationship between the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what, as you put it, anger and non-anger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it requires a discernment of the principle of that relationship.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's... that's what the relationship is.
[SPEAKER_01]: To even be able to dwell in non-anger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: To be able to properly establish in a state of non-anger.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like in this particular example.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what people fail to see, because... yes, everybody can value silence over talking, we can feel more peaceful and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody can see as fast, it requires more determination, more... more resolve, makes your mind stronger.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, none of them sees it in a... in a... in a... in a relationship, like, eh... silence in a relationship to speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: And... because if you were to see it, then even when you're not silent, you will be partaking in silence.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't be affected by speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you were to see the proper order, proper relationship between fast... phenomenon of fasting in your experience and phenomenon of eating in your experience, then, if your mind would be properly established upon the discernment of that relationship, not upon the act of fast... the act of fasting doesn't establish you, doesn't establish your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha said that self-mortification won't result in liberation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to do it to an extent until you discern the perception of the phenomenon of it,
[SPEAKER_01]: But doing it in itself doesn't necessarily... well, for sure, it doesn't free you, it doesn't do anything for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's discernment of the principle in relation to eating, from the point of view of fasting.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what... that knowledge is what establishes your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, basically, whenever you're eating, you won't be affected by that eating.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would remain properly established.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be pulled by the food.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you overcome sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: In that in that example, in the example of a state of non-anger, which is really greater even for angry people, it's more common.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not angry.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just when you have the burst of anger, that's what you focus on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can spend all your time being non-angry and still remain an angry person, if you don't discern the principle between non-anger and anger, that can then free your mind from anger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you won't be affected by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What about wholesome and unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_01]: Same.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the most general.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wholesome and unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensuality is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-sensuality is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anger is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-anger is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of these things I'm talking about, these examples, would come down to even a more general example, which is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Abandon everything unwholesome by discerning the relationship between wholesome and unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I was thinking, you only
[SPEAKER_00]: Notice the dependence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dependence.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you want to go higher, if you want to have higher, if you want to attain higher wisdoms, it's a biggocenic bit.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know, a wholesomeness to
[SPEAKER_00]: It's determined by the not... the unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a way, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's defined by...
[SPEAKER_00]: So... but when you notice that, it leads you higher.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... that's what I meant when I was saying in the past, I don't know if you meant somebody else, I think I even wrote about it, that when you start keeping the precepts and you begin, you have to keep the precepts, but then if the wisdom starts to be developed,
[SPEAKER_01]: Through a practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you don't keep them, they keep you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the precepts are not about what things you should be doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more about the behaviors that you're not doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the negative aspect of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what this establishes with.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not you're actively holding on to precepts that kind of gives you a buffer zone and a boundary and a safety net.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's things that you don't do, that you discern through doing the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what are the things that you don't do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Unwholesome things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the negative behavior in regard to unwholesome things.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what defines, then, that basis for practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's exactly that thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can be wholesome all your life, but not discern relationship, you know, to unwholesome...
[SPEAKER_01]: In the heart of everything wholesome you do, there is the opposite possibility present as a phenomenon, as something that's not being done at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, at the same time, there is something that's done, which automatically defines something else as not done.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that needs to be seen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you see that thing that you don't do, and your mind that discerns it, then that becomes your establishment.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you don't have to do even what you were doing, in order to maintain that establishment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, it's simply you not having to do anything is what establishes you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not having to do unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, by discerning that you're not doing unwholesome, you don't have to do wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you get established.
[SPEAKER_01]: By not discerning that you're not doing unwholesome, you have to actively keep doing wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you don't go beyond the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by discerning, what I'm talking about, you should discern, that's how you go beyond good and evil, as they would say.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by discerning that you are not doing evil, you don't have to do good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say, if it's to establish your mind on metta, kindness, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Really, it's not very good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You establish metta,
[SPEAKER_01]: By discerning the phenomenon of not... by basically by not engaging with the phenomenon of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by doing non-ill-will, or rather by not doing ill-will, you establish loving-kindness automatically.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are not emulating or fabricating or cultivating actively loving-kindness.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You do it in a negative way, in a sense of
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the recognition of negative things, of things that are not done.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean by negative thinking, not done.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's automatically that which is not included in that which is not done, is what's done.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because in that example of kindness, if if I wanted to develop kindness, and then I went out and I wanted kind things to do, okay,
[SPEAKER_00]: Smile at people, say good morning, you know, stare them in the eye, find out ways you can help them.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's... that's very different.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a very different way to work.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... that is better to do than being rude to people.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the first step, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: If somebody engages in ill-will, it's good that they start doing the actual kindness.
[SPEAKER_01]: By doing the actual kindness, they can start discerning that they are not doing their ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: The more they discern the phenomenon of ill-will and their lack of engagement with it, the greater they get established in the opposite, which is non-ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is kindness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is automatically kindness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, they don't have to keep bringing acts of kindness and emulating kindness in order to get the state or phenomenon of kindness, because they automatically have it through the state of non-ill-will that they have established.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to start, like, you have to start fasting a bit, to restrain yourself in regard to the food, to then recognize that the state of not eating is actually more fundamental than the state of eating.
[SPEAKER_01]: You spend far more time not eating than eating.
[SPEAKER_01]: You spend far more time not engaged with food than engaged with food.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, you give all the priority to the food, when the food is the food.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can have that in theory as much as you like, but you won't discern the principle until you actually start fasting.
[SPEAKER_01]: To a degree.
[SPEAKER_01]: Restraining yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not constantly just chugging the food down your throat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then, you can start discerning that principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you discern the principle, then, yeah, you don't have to keep holding on to your fasting and stuff, because you will automatically be restrained in regard to the food.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's basically the whole point of sīla.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's exactly the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And how you overcome it is a factor.
[SPEAKER_01]: A sīla bhārata paramāsa needs to be taken.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it is a fetter.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's a better fetter than the fetters of sensuality and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you replace it initially, so that you can come out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And a Sotāpanna would overcome Sīlavāda Paramāsa by... by what I'm telling you now, basically, by this description.
[SPEAKER_01]: By taking it, in order to discern the principle in regard to the phenomenon of wholesome, phenomenon of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you are bound by your discernment, your full knowledge of the phenomenon of not wholesome,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you're automatically wholesome, even if you don't actively, neurotically, tightly think about the actual things you must not do, and the rules, and whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, your behavior becomes natural, naturally aligned with the rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: Give or take, obviously.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, fundamentally, you can't do anything that's truly unwholesome, in a sense that would compromise the virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even when Āryas in the suttas would sort of forget about the principle, and then they would commit loads of offenses, as the Buddha would say, sometimes grave offenses, really, all they would have to do is re-establish the principle, and their purity is back.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the drunk and the sotāpanna was just drinking and drinking and not practicing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, oh, he composed his mind toward the end of his life, basically, and he recognized which is greater.
[SPEAKER_01]: Death or life?
[SPEAKER_01]: Death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is greater, not eating or eating?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not eating.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, he recognizes that principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is greater, not drinking or drinking?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is greater, non-sensuality or sensuality?
[SPEAKER_01]: By recognizing his mind is established.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_01]: Cellulous or non-cellulous?
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because most people are basically not engaging in non-celibate acts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Most people will be celibate if you look at their behavior, in the sense of they're not constantly engaging in sexual intercourse, for example.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they're not really celibate, because the mind is fully bound with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you will be celibate, well, first by taking the determination to be celibate, and then by discerning the principle, which is greater, which is more fundamental, and discerning the relationship between the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, simply by not engaging in sensuality, you are a non-sensual person.
[SPEAKER_00]: You go beyond sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if we go to guarding the doors of the senses,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, distraction?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensual distraction?
[SPEAKER_00]: Non-sensual or non-distraction?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Non-distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a sensual distraction, then there is a distraction that's a non-sensual distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I couldn't help but say it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then there is a non-distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't just leap from sensual distraction to a complete non-distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to replace sensual distraction with a non-sensual distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: which is basically, uh, holding on to right... holding on to views and you, uh, virtue and you're still about the paramāsa will be a non-sensual distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's still on the level of action.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to do that in order to replace the very unwholesome, sensual distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: By not engaging in sensual distraction by body, by speech, you will eventually be able to not engage by mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will be able to do so.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you then abandon, you overcome the non-sensual distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when non-sensual distraction cannot enter you, what can be said for that which is even inferior to it, which is a sensual distraction, that becomes inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I meant, like, you replace the grief of the household life with the grief of renunciation, of a life of a monk.
[SPEAKER_01]: You replace the joys of household life with the joys of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see it as greater, structurally, fundamentally, phenomenologically greater as a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more fundamental.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same, you will be abiding in a noble silence simply by stopping mid-sentence, if you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could establish your mind to that point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereby, yeah, you're not in silence when you're talking.
[SPEAKER_01]: The moment you stop talking, the mind goes back into silence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it never left.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't do that if you never practice silence.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you never practice restraint of your speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you've just been chatting and talking constantly whenever there's an impulse to do so.
[SPEAKER_01]: But obviously, you certainly won't do that either if you just, for the rest of your life, refuse to utter a word.
[SPEAKER_01]: That won't necessarily reveal you the principle between speaking and non-speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: The verb of determination.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's you trying to discern the principle, being pointed at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That might make you help discern it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why you can't put the proper practice of dhamma that results in wisdom in any method or technique, because it's not about what you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about the recognition between things that you do and you don't do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's neither where you do it nor where you don't do.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't pin down the practice in a mere mechanical behavior or repetition or avoidance of certain things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, avoidance of unwholesome is necessary as a basis, but that's not a dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha was quite clear when he said that dhamma is not vinaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not vinaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's as clear as that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because many people, many monks can't distinguish that.
[SPEAKER_01]: They think if there's no vinaya, there's no dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dhamma is not vinaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: A very clear statement.
[SPEAKER_01]: Followed by, but there is no practice of dhamma without presence of vinaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without presence of urge.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, aha!
[SPEAKER_01]: There is something to be understood there.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you understand that, you will be free from sīla dharmās.
[SPEAKER_01]: You truly understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is basically what I'm expounding on here.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I'm trying to explain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your non-sensual behavior needs to become established.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to actually do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because by doing a non-sensual behavior, you can't at the same time do the sensual behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, yeah, you can spend the rest of your life neurotic and focused about your rules and virtue and never discern the principle in regard to, hold on, it's not about me doing the virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: My virtue is actually defined by not doing the non-virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's a completely different thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why you can't put the practice into certain
[SPEAKER_01]: A meditation, or just watch that, to do this, or walk like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It makes no sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: At all.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it comes down to...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you recognize that, actually, what I'm supposed to do is discern the principle between wholesome and unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha would, like, to Mahāpajāpati, when she asked him to go on a retreat and give her a brief instruction, all he said was, whatever you know is unwholesome, abandon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever you know is wholesome, cultivate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, she went in the mountains based on that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can see that cultivating unwholesome... sorry, cultivating wholesome means basically cultivate, I mean, discern, dwell on it, bother on it, bring it into being until it's understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because she wasn't in the mountain and doing charity work or some other wholesome things that people usually regard as good.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, she was completely secluded.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when it's said to be cultivating wholesome, it means, yeah, you don't do unwholesome,
[SPEAKER_01]: You're already calculating wholesome, when you know that that's what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're unaware of the principle that by not doing unwholesome, you're automatically wholesome, so you don't have to then do wholesome, if you don't discern that principle, you remain bound by wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Consequently, you remain bound by unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why sheer adherence to the rules and virtue can result in good rebirth, because you've been doing good actions, but it cannot take you outside of the sphere of kamma, sphere of action.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's only reserved for those with the right view, which is where the dhamma begins, where the right view begins.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you was in a relationship... that's why I'm so insistent when people come and ask me questions that... that they don't...
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't focus, don't think you can put it in a technique or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they say, oh, I find it helpful or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your criteria of what's helpful, it's not right, or it's not existent very often.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what's helpful is just what feels good for most people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you adhere to something, you think, this is what I should be doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, that's definition of sīla bhārata-pāramāsa, virtue and duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need to be doing this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's a first factor.
[SPEAKER_01]: A first factor that prevents you from becoming another.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you... you then... well, if a person has some transparency, they will think, okay, so, I can either adhere to this neurotically for the rest of my life and do this... do this technique and whatnot, and remain a Bhutujana, or I can really figure out what it meant by that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because these are the words of the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Sīlabhata Paramahansa, it's basically a definition of virtue and duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a first factor.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the object of a composure?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you know what the object is?
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: As opposed to the unwholesome I'm not doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that would be the... Yeah, because you can call that object as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: But most people... What is an object?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: A smiley face, a clay pot, a buddha rūpa or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: An object.
[SPEAKER_01]: Give me an object.
[SPEAKER_01]: Give me something palpable.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: A recognition of unwholesome, if that's your present thought, is the object that you can focus on.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a result of it, you will discern the relationship between the wholesome, that's automatically being defined, simply by not engaging in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, another thing I was thinking about, then, in terms of... if one sees that, again, I'm not engaging in unwholesome acts, therefore I dwell in wholesomeness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Quite.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a peaceful state, afflictive, but not active.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, well, one is determined by the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then it says that neither are mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I think, what is higher then?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the higher perception then?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's what I'm talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going beyond good and evil, good and bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the higher perception is self?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not self?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fundamentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that is already reserved only for the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, putusas can have higher perceptions in regard to sensuality, in regard to virtue and duties, all the upādānas that they can free themselves from, in regard to views,
[SPEAKER_01]: But they can't have a high perception in regard to self and not-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they do so, they'll become a Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it is exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I'm talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: The discernment of the relationship of wholesome and unwholesome takes you above wholesome and unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: It takes you above things that you were doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It takes you above action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means it cannot be appropriate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because only things that you can do are appropriate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things on that level are things that are regarded as mine, for me, as myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that you can exercise even, like, rudimentary levels of control.
[SPEAKER_01]: That sense of control is a necessary basis for a sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is the sense of self, so to think.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you go beyond in terms of the discernment of that relationship, that means that neither that and also... well, that means that you will see that, yeah, wholesome is defined by
[SPEAKER_01]: That which is not done in terms of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, consequently, unwholesome is the absence of wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is no need for you to hold on to anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those things define itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's determinations.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why ignorance of those... of that... the determination relationships results in appropriation of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where Vijaya is the first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-ignorance of that relationship results in dissolvement of ownership of that relationship.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't own either good or bad, either wholesome or unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: You go beyond it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because your actions are completely unnecessary, redundant.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no room for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unwholesome is defined by wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wholesome is the absence of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: But obviously, for as long as your behavior has been engaging in unwholesome, you've been perpetuating that mistake, maintaining that mistaken view.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you can see self and not hold even to self... Then, it's automatically not self.
[SPEAKER_00]: But self is still there as something that you don't hold.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's not yourself then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because self is defined not by what is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Self is defined by whether what's there is being held as mine or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by seeing self as something there, that means it already can be regarded as not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you see what I mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: So... That sense of self that would be there, if seen as not self, sorry, as not mine, first it needs to be acknowledged, the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you deny there is no self, there is no self, you'll never see that which is yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you start seeing it, you start seeing it as a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's a phenomenon, it's something that has a reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's something that has a reason, it cannot be that master behind the arising, behind the manifestation, that controller.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's manifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just partakes in the same thing, shares the same nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but that's possible to see only once.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that is higher than mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in a way, you can use that reflection, like, which is greater, not mine or mine?
[SPEAKER_01]: In general, what is more?
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that don't belong to you or things that belong to you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, things that don't belong to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's far more numerous in this world.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is greater than things that belong to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you can use simply that discernment on a quite mundane level, in a way, and actually develop your mind on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you stick to it, discerning it, you would see that then whatever is yours, it's completely gratuitously, accidentally solved.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you're not in control of things that are taken to be yours, which means, oh, they're not really mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're... basically, things that are yours are really things that are not yours, that are just closer to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're things that are really not, not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like, oh, this is not mine, and this is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, this is not my... not, not mine, and this is not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, fundamentally, none of it is yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of it is not mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, for an arahant,
[SPEAKER_00]: Not mine is higher than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because not mine is opposed to mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's what an Ārya needs to keep doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why he said, not I am, not mine, not myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the reflection of Ārya.
[SPEAKER_01]: He goes back.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't even need to do that anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: It ceased completely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Notions of mine and not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Notions of wholesome and unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Notions of good and bad have gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: He went beyond.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eightfold path he went beyond.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is the highest determination?
[SPEAKER_00]: Determination that he...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know what I'm trying to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the highest... What is the highest thing he sees?
[SPEAKER_00]: This is determined by that.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is determined.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here's what he sees.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Determinations have ceased.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Determinations have ceased.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's determined by all his previous efforts towards ceasing determinations.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's irreversible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is nothing dependent on... That's still undetermined.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Asaṅgata, yeah?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the definition of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing dependent on anything anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing taking his mind anywhere, anyhow, in any manner, any shape or form at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Possibility is gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't need to say it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And about life and death.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, would you say that
[SPEAKER_00]: There's life, there's activity.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what is higher than that?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is greater than that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Death would be more fundamental.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because if life would be more fundamental, death would just not be manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, but there's something different as, like, say, there's anger, non-anger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's different because it kind of involves you in your entirety.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anger, not anger, offers you some perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of... but this is life and not life.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I can't stop doing life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Life and death are basically on the level of nibbāna and not nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're determined.
[SPEAKER_01]: Determined and undetermined, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in the same manner, when I say, like, the fact... if you recognize that you can die at any moment,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, your whole life, anything, your past, your future, your hopes, everything, your fears, your desires, everything, everything, your family, everything, it's just... it becomes quite insignificant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: It all goes away and you cannot possibly prevent it in any manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you truly contemplate that, you realize how circumstantial
[SPEAKER_01]: Your entire life, there is no greatness of it, or priority of it, or certain personal values.
[SPEAKER_01]: Completely, it could have been otherwise.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the recognition, like, oh, the one that the Buddha corrected, like, oh, it could not be for me, it will not be for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the Buddha corrected it in saying, it won't be for me, it will not be for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in,
[SPEAKER_01]: The greatest of the protugenous views, they would have said, are the ones, it could not, it could have not been for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is kind of, basically, almost surmounts the entire life.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't quite get the whole relationship thing between the sankhāra and sankhātadhamma, between the determined.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can abandon a lot.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the one who gets a lesson, he will say it will not, if not for sure, that in the future won't be for him, because there is no room for the ownership in the present, nor in the past, nor in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: So he corrects that statement just slightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like from a first person to a third person.
[SPEAKER_01]: Something I forgot, it's been a long time since I read it.